<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
        <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
        <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
        <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
        <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
        ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        category="std"
        docName="draft-ietf-scim-events-02"
        ipr="trust200902"
        updates=""
        submissionType="IETF"
        xml:lang="en"
        tocInclude="true"
        tocDepth="3"
        symRefs="true"
        sortRefs="true"
        consensus="true"
        version="3" >
    <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.1 -->
    <front>
        <title abbrev="draft-ietf-scim-events">SCIM Profile for Security Event Tokens</title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-scim-events"/>
        <author fullname="Phil Hunt" initials="P." role="editor" surname="Hunt">
            <organization abbrev="IndependentId">Independent Identity Inc</organization>
            <address>
                <email>phil.hunt@independentid.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Nancy Cam-Winget" initials="N." surname="Cam-Winget">
            <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems</organization>
            <address>
                <email>ncamwing@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Mike Kiser" initials="M." surname="Kiser">
            <organization abbrev="Sailpoint">Sailpoint Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>mike.kiser@sailpoint.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2023" month="July" day="10"/>
        <workgroup>SCIM</workgroup>

        <keyword>Identity</keyword>
        <keyword>Event</keyword>
        <keyword>SET</keyword>
        <keyword>Provisioning</keyword>
        <keyword>Token</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <keyword>SCIM</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This specification defines a set of SCIM Security Events using the Security Event Token Specification
                RFC8417 to enable the asynchronous exchange of messages between SCIM Service Providers
                and receivers. SCIM Security Events are typically used for: asynchronous request completion, resource
                replication, provisioning co-ordination, and shared security signals.
            </t>
        </abstract>

    </front>
    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>Introduction and Overview</name>
            <t>
                This specification defines Security Events for SCIM Service Providers and receivers as specified by the
                Security Event Tokens (SET) <xref target="RFC8417" format="default"/> specification. Scim Security
                Events in this specification include: asynchronous request completion, resource replication,
                provisioning co-ordination, and security signals.
            </t>
            <t>
                This specification also profiles the use of the HTTP Header "<tt>Prefer: Async-response</tt>" <xref target="RFC7240"/>
                to allow a SCIM Protocol Client <xref target="RFC7644"/> to request an asynchronous response (see <xref target="asyncRequest"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
                In a typical HTTP client-server relationship, a SCIM Protocol Client issues commands to a SCIM Service
                Provider using HTTP methods such as POST, PATCH, and DELETE <xref target="RFC7644" format="default"/>
                that cause a state change to a SCIM Resource. When multiple independent SCIM Clients update SCIM
                resources, individual clients become out of date as state changes occur. Some clients may need to be
                informed of these changes for co-ordination or reconciliation purposes. This could be done using SCIM
                periodic SCIM GET requests over time, but this rapidly problematic as the number of changes and the
                number of resources increases.
            </t>
            <t>
                Security Event Tokens <xref target="RFC8417"/> and SCIM Events offers the ability to exchange
                messages that act as triggers for receivers to monitor over time in an asynchronous approach. This
                enables greater scale and timeliness, where only changed information is exchanged between parties.
            </t>
            <t>
                A SET token conveys a signal about a state changes that has occurred in a publishing SCIM Service Provider.
                That token may be of interest to one or more receivers and can be delivered asynchronously to the originating
                SCIM client making the change. Unlike SCIM Protocol requests which convey protocol commands, Security
                Events describe statements of fact about changes that have already occurred at the SCIM Provider. This
                approach allows the event receiver to determine the best local follow-up action to take within the
                context of the receiver. For example, the receiver can reconcile intentional schema and population
                differences between the domain as the receiver.
            </t>

            <section>
                <name>Requirements Language</name>
                <t>The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                    "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
                    RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
                    interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
                    <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
                    all capitals, as shown here.</t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="notat" toc="default" numbered="true">
                <name>Notational Conventions</name>
                <t>
                    For purposes of readability examples are not URL encoded.
                    Implementers MUST percent encode URLs as described in <xref target="RFC3986" format="default">
                    Section 2.1 of</xref>.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Throughout this document all figures MAY contain spaces and extra
                    line-wrapping for readability and space limitations. Similarly, some
                    URI's contained within examples, have been shortened for space and
                    readability reasons.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="defs" toc="default" numbered="true">
                <name>Definitions</name>
                <t>
                    This specification uses definitions from the following specifications:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>Json Web Tokens (JWT) <xref target="RFC7519"/>, </li>
                    <li>Security Event Tokens (SET) <xref target="RFC8417"
                                                    format="default"/>, and</li>
                    <li>System for Cross-Domain Identity Management Protocol <xref target="RFC7644"/>.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <t>
                    In Json Web Tokens and Security Event Tokens the term "claim" is used to refer to JSON attribute
                    values in a Json Web Token <xref target="RFC7519"/> structure. The term "claim" in tokens is used
                    to indicate that an attribute value may not be verified and its accuracy can be questioned. In the
                    context of SCIM, claims are referred to as attributes. For the purposes of this specification claims
                    and attributes are inter-changeable. For consistency, JWT and SET IANA registered attributes will
                    continue to be called claims, while event attributes (i.e. those in an event payload) will be
                    referred to as attributes.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Additionally, the following terms are defined:
                </t>
                <dl newline="true">
                    <dt>Attributes and Claims</dt>
                    <dd>
                        The JWT specification <xref target="RFC7519"/> upon which SET is based uses the term "claims" to
                        refer to attributes in a JSON token. SCIM in contrast uses the term "attributes" to refer to
                        JSON attributes. For the purposes of this draft, the terms "attributes" and "claims" are equivalent.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>CP</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Abbreviation for "Co-ordinated Provisioning" as defined in <xref target="coordination"/>. In these
                        relationships an Event Publisher and Receiver typically exchange resource change events without
                        exchanging data. For a receiver to know the value of the data, the Event Receiver usually
                        has calls back to the SCIM Event Publisher domain to receive a new copy of data (e.g. Uses a
                        SCIM GET request).
                    </dd>

                    <dt>DBR</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Abbreviation for "Domain Based Replication" as defined in <xref target="replication"/>. In this
                        mode because there is an administrative relationship spanning multiple operational domains, data
                        shared in Events typically uses the <tt>full</tt> mode variation of change events including
                        the <tt>data</tt> payload attribute. This eliminates the need for a call
                        back to retrieve additional data.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>Event Feed / Event Stream</dt>
                    <dd>
                        This describes the quality that a feed (aka stream) MAY be managed per receiving client.
                        A SET transfer (see <xref target="RFC8935"/> <xref target="RFC8936"/>) service provider MAY
                        offer to allow Event Receiver's to "subscribe" to specific event types or events about specific
                        resources (see Feed Management events <xref target="scimFeedEvents"/>).
                    </dd>

                    <dt>Event Receiver</dt>
                    <dd>
                        An entity receives events typically via <xref target="RFC8935"/>, <xref target="RFC8936"/>, or
                        HTTP GET (see <xref target="asyncRequest"/>). In the case of SET Push Transfer
                        <xref target="RFC8935"/>, the Event Receiver is an HTTP Service Endpoint that receives requests.
                        In the case of SET Poll-Based Transfer <xref target="RFC8936"/>, the receiver is an HTTP client
                        that initiates HTTP request to an Event Publisher endpoint.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>Event Publisher</dt>
                    <dd>
                        A system that issues SET tokens based on a resource state changes that have occurred at a SCIM
                        Service Provider. For example, events MAY be the result of a SCIM Create, Modify, or Delete
                        as defined in <xref target="RFC7644"/>. A SCIM Service Provider MAY be an Event Publisher or an
                        independent service that aggregates events into Event Receiver feeds. As described above, when
                        using <xref target="RFC8935"/>, the Event Publisher is an HTTP Client that initiates HTTP POST
                        requests to a defined Event Receiver endpoint. When using <xref target="RFC8936"/>, the Event
                        Publisher provides an HTTP endpoint which a receiver MAY use to "poll" for Security Events.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>RS</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Abbreviation for "Risk Signals" as defined in <xref target="s_risk" />.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>SCIM Client</dt>
                    <dd>
                        An HTTP client that initiates SCIM Protocol <xref target="RFC7644"/> requests and receives
                        responses.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>SCIM Service Provider</dt>
                    <dd>
                        An HTTP server that implements SCIM Protocol <xref target="RFC7644"/> and SCIM Schema
                        <xref target="RFC7643"/>.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>SET</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Abbreviation for "Security Event Token" as defined in <xref target="RFC8417"/>
                    </dd>

                </dl>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="scimEvents" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>SCIM Events</name>
            <t>
                A SCIM event is a signal, in the form of a Security Event Token <xref target="RFC8417" format="default"/>
                that describe some event that has occurred. A SET event consists of a set of standard JWT "top-level"
                claims, an "events" claim that contains one or more event URI subclaims (JSON attributes) each with a
                JSON object containing relevant event information.
            </t>
            <section anchor="sub-id" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Identifying the Subject of an Event</name>
                <t>
                    SCIM Events SHALL use the "sub_id" claim defined by <xref target="SUBID">Subject Identifiers for
                    Security Event Tokens</xref> specification to identify the subject of events. The <tt>sub_id</tt>
                    claim MUST be contained within the main JWT claims body and SHALL NOT be located within an Event
                    payload within the <tt>events</tt> claim. A SET with multiple event URI's indicates that the events
                    arise from the same transaction or resource state change for a single resource or subject. Finally,
                    as recommended in <xref target="RFC8417"/> the JWT "sub" claim SHALL NOT be used.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="example_subid">
                    <name>SCIM Subject Id Example</name>
                    <artwork type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
     "iss": "issuer.example.com",
     "iat": 1508184845,
     "aud": "aud.example.com",
     "sub_id": {
        "format": "scim",
        "uri": "/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462",
        "externalId": "alice@example.com"
     },
     "events": {
       ...
     }
}]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    The top-level claim "sub_id" SHALL contain the subclaim "format" whose value is set to <tt>scim</tt> to indicate
                    the other attributes present are SCIM attributes. The following sub_id attributes are defined:
                </t>
                <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                    <dt>uri</dt>
                    <dd>
                        The SCIM relative path for the resource which usually consists of the resource type endpoint
                        plus the resource <tt>id</tt>. For example <tt>/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462</tt>.
                        This attributes MUST be provided in a SCIM Event <tt>sub_id</tt> claim. Note the relative path
                        is the path component after the SCIM Service Provider Base URI as defined in Section 1.3 <xref target="RFC7644"/>.
                        In cases where the Event Receiver is unable to match a URI, the Event Receiver MAY issue a call-back
                        to a previously agreed SCIM Service Provider Base URI plus the relative <tt>uri</tt> value and
                        perform a SCIM GET request per Section 3.4.1 <xref target="RFC7644"/>.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>externalId</dt>
                    <dd>
                        If known, the <tt>externalId</tt> value of the SCIM Resource that MAY be used by a receiver to identify
                        the corresponding resource in the Event Receiver's domain.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>id</dt>
                    <dd>
                        The SCIM Id attribute MAY be used for backwards compatibility reasons in addition to the
                        <tt>uri</tt> claim.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>emails,username, ...</dt>
                    <dd>A SCIM attribute that is unique to both the Event Publisher and Receiver. Typically, attributes
                        like email or usernames are used in situations where normal SCIM identifiers ( <tt>id</tt> and
                        <tt>externalId</tt>) are insufficient to identify a common resource between an Event Publisher
                        and Event Receiver.</dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="attributes" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Common Event Attributes</name>
                <t>The following attributes are available for all events defined. Some attributes are defined as SET/JWT
                    claims, while others are "Event Payload" claims as defined in Section 1.2 <xref target="RFC8417"/>.
                </t>
                <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                    <dt>txn</dt>
                    <dd>
                        For the purposes of SCIM, this SET defined claim identifies a unique transaction
                        originating at a SCIM Service Provider and/or its underlying data repository or database. The
                        claim is used to detect duplicate transactions that may have been received (e.g. in the case of
                        a re-transmitted or recovered event). If not provided, the SET <tt>jti</tt> claim MAY be used.
                        Where <tt>txn</tt> identifies a unique transaction within a SCIM Service Provider, multiple SETs
                        MAY be issued each with distinct JTI's stemming from a common originating transaction with identical
                        <tt>txn</tt> values.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>data</dt>
                    <dd>
                        This event payload attribute contains information described in SCIM Bulk
                        Operations <tt>data</tt> attribute, Section 3.7 <xref target="RFC7644"/>. The JSON object
                        contains the equivalent SCIM command processed by the SCIM Service provider. For example, after
                        processing a SCIM Create operation, the data contained includes the final representation of the
                        created entity by the SCIM Service Provider including the assigned <tt>id</tt> value.
                    </dd>

                    <dt>attributes</dt>
                    <dd>
                        This payload attribute contains an array of attributes that were added, revised, or removed. For example: <br/>
                         <tt>"attributes": ["username","emails"]</tt>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
                <t>
                    Only one of <tt>data</tt> or <tt>attributes</tt> claims SHALL be provided depending on the event
                    definition.
                </t>

                <t>
                    This specifications defines a new URI prefix <tt>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event</tt> which is used
                    as the prefix for the following defined SCIM Events (see <xref target="IANAevents"/>).
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="scimFeedEvents" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>SCIM Feed Events</name>
                <t>
                    This section defines events related to changes in the content of an event feed. For example,
                    SCIM resources that are being added or removed from an event feed. For example, the events may be
                    used in Co-operative Provisioning scenarios where only a sub-set of entities are shared across an
                    Event Feed. The URI prefix for these events is:
                    <tt>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed</tt>
                </t>
                <section anchor="feedAdd" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:add</name>
                    <t>The specified resource was added to the Event Feed. A <tt>feed:add</tt> does not indicate a
                        resource is new or has been recently created. For example,
                        an existing user has had a new role (e.g. CRM_User) added to
                        their profile which has caused their resource to join a feed.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="exampleFeedAddEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Feed Add Event</name>
                        <artwork type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "txn": "b7b953f11cc6489bbfb87834747cc4c1",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462",
    "externalId": "jdoe"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:add": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="feedRemove" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:remove</name>
                    <t>The specified
                        resource has been removed from the feed. Removal does not indicate
                        that the resource was deleted or otherwise deactivated. This
                        event has minimal disclosure.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="exampleRemoveEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Feed Remove Event</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462"
    "externalId": "jdoe",
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:remove": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section anchor="scimProvEvents" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>SCIM Provisioning Events</name>
                <t>
                    This section defines resource changes that have occurred within a SCIM Service Provider. These
                    events are used in both Domain Based Replication (DBR) and Co-operative Provisioning (CP) mode. The
                    URI prefix for these events is: <tt>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov</tt>
                </t>
                <section anchor="provCreate" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:create:{notice|full}</name>
                    <t>
                        Indicates a new SCIM resource has been created by the SCIM Service Provider
                        and has been added to the Event Feed. When the <tt>data</tt> payload attribute is included, the
                        event uri SHALL end with <tt>full</tt> otherwise, the event URI ends with <tt>notice</tt>. In
                        full mode, the set of values reflecting the final state of the resource at the service provider
                        are provided using the <tt>data</tt> attribute. In <tt>notice</tt> mode,
                        <tt>attributes</tt> is returned disclosing the list of attributes included in the create request.
                        Note that because the event MAY be used for replication, the final <tt>id</tt>
                        attribute that was assigned by the SCIM Service Provider is shared so that all replicas in the
                        domain MAY use the same resource identifier.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="exampleCreateEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Create (Full)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "4d3559ec67504aaba65d40b0363faad8",

  "iat": 1458496404,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
    "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754",
    "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/5d7604516b1d08641d7676ee7"
  ],
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9",
     "externalId":"jdoe"
  }
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:create:full":{
      "data":{
        "schemas":[ "urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:core:2.0:User"],
        "emails":[
          {"type":"work","value":"jdoe@example.com"}
        ],
        "userName":"jdoe",
        "name":{
          "givenName":"John",
          "familyName":"Doe"
        }
      }
    }
  }
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                    <figure anchor="exampleCreateEventDef">
                        <name>Example SCIM Create Event (Notice)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "4d3559ec67504aaba65d40b0363faad8",
  "iat": 1458496404,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
    "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754",
    "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/5d7604516b1d08641d7676ee7"
  ],
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9",
    "externalId": "jdoe"
  },
  "events": {
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:create:notice": {
      "attributes": [
        "id",
        "name",
        "userName",
        "password",
        "emails"
      ]
    }
  }
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        The event above notifies the Event Receiver which attributes
                        have changed but does not convey
                        the actual information. The Event Receiver MAY retrieve that information
                        by performing a SCIM GET to the <tt>sub</tt> value specified.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="provPatch" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:patch:{notice|full}</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource has been updated using SCIM PATCH. In <tt>full</tt> mode, the
                        <tt>data</tt> payload attribute is included. When the event URI ends with <tt>notice</tt>, the
                        list of attributes changed is provided.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="examplePatchEventFull">
                        <name>Example SCIM Patch Event (Full)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Groups/176f397ec4c44b94b2cfcb759780b8c2",
    "externalId": "crmUsers"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:patch:full": {
      "version": "a330bc54f0671c9",
      "data": {
        "schemas":
      ["urn:ietf:params:scim:api:messages:2.0:PatchOp"],
        "Operations":[{
          "op":"add",
          "path":"members",
          "value":[{
             "display": "Babs Jensen",
             "$ref": "/Users/2819c223...413861904646",
             "value": "2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646"
          }]
        }]
      }
    }
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure anchor="examplePatchEventBrief">
                        <name>Example SCIM Patch Event (Notice)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Groups/176f397ec4c44b94b2cfcb759780b8c2",
    "externalId": "crmUsers"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:patc:notice": {
      "attributes": ["members"],
      "version": "a330bc54f0671c9"
    }
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="provPut" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:put:{notice|full}</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource has been updated (e.g. one or more attributes has
                        changed). In <tt>full</tt> mode, the SCIM PUT request body is included in the <tt>data</tt>
                        attribute. In <tt>notice</tt> mode the modified attributes are listed using <tt>attributes</tt>.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="examplePutEventFull">
                        <name>Example SCIM Put Event (Full)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:put:full": {
      "version": "a330bc54f0671c9",
      "data": {
        "schemas":["urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:core:2.0:User"],
        "userName":"jdoe",
        "externalId":"jdoe",
        "name":{
           "formatted":"Mr. Jon Jack Doe III",
           "familyName":"Doe",
           "givenName":"Jon",
           "middleName":"Jack"
        },
        "roles":[],
        "emails":[
          {"value":"jdoe@example.com"},
          {"value":"anon@jdoe.org"}
        ]
      }
    }
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure anchor="examplePutEventBrief">
                        <name>Example SCIM Put Event (Notice)</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:put:notice": {
      "version": "a330bc54f0671c9",
      "attributes": ["userName","externalId","name","roles","emails"]
    }
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                </section>

                <section anchor="provDelete" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:delete</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource has been deleted from the SCIM Service Provider.
                        The resource is also removed from the feed. When a
                        DELETE is sent, a corresponding <tt>feedRemove</tt> is not issued. A delete
                        event has no payload attributes. Note that because the delete event has
                        no attributes, the qualifiers <tt>full</tt> and <tt>notice</tt> SHALL NOT be used.
                    </t>

                    <figure anchor="exampleDeleteEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Delete Event</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462",
    "externalId": "jDoe"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:delete": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="provActivate" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:activate</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource (e.g. User) has been "activated". This does not necessarily reflect
                        any particular state change at the SCIM Service Provider but may simply indicate the
                        account defined by the SCIM resource is ready for use as agreed upon by the Event Publisher and
                        Event Receiver. For example, an activated resource represents an account that may be logged in.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="exampleActivateEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Activate Event</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2b2f880af6674ac284bae9381673d462"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:activate": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="provDeactivate" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:deactivate</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource (e.g. User) has been deactivated and
                        disabled. The exact meaning SHOULD be agreed to by the Event Publisher
                        and its corresponding Event Receiver. Typically, this means the sub
                        may no longer have an active security session. As with the activate
                        event, this event has minimal disclosure requirements.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section anchor="scimSignals" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>SCIM Signals Events</name>
                <t>
                    This section defines security signal events that have occurred within a
                    SCIM Service Provider.The URI prefix for these events is:
                    <tt>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:signal</tt>
                </t>
                <section anchor="authMethod" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:authMethod</name>
                    <t>
                        A new authentication method has been added to the User profile. As attackers often use new
                        authentication methods to lock-out Users from their account, this signal can be used by the
                        receiver that the chance of account them may be temporarily elevated. The receiver MAY also
                        wish to take action such as resetting current authorizations or sessions.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="exampleAuthMethod">
                        <name>Example SCIM Authentication Factor Change Event</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "3d0c3cf797584bd193bd0fb1bd4e7d30",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9"
  },
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:authMethod": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458496025,
  "iss": "https://scim.example.com"
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="sigPassReset" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:pwdReset</name>
                    <t>
                        The specified resource (e.g. User) has changed its password or the password
                        has been reset. When the password has changed, the
                        <tt>attributes</tt>
                        attribute is supplied with the value "password".
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="examplePassword">
                        <name>Example SCIM Password Change Event</name>
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "3d0c3cf797584bd193bd0fb1bd4e7d30",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/44f6142df96bd6ab61e7521d9"
  },
  "events": {
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:pwdReset": {}
  },
  "iat": 1458496025,
  "iss": "https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
    "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754",
    "https://jhub.example.com/Feeds/5d7604516b1d08641d7676ee7"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section anchor="scimMisc" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Miscellaneous Events</name>
                <t>
                    This section defines events related miscellaneous events such as Asynchronous Request completion that have occurred within a
                    SCIM Service Provider. The URI prefix for these events is:
                    <tt>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:misc</tt>
                </t>

                <section anchor="asyncEvent" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Asynchronous Events</name>
                    <section anchor="asyncRequest" numbered="true" toc="default">
                        <name>Making an Asynchronous SCIM Request</name>
                        <t>
                            A SCIM client making SCIM HTTP requests defined in <xref target="RFC7644"/> MAY request
                            "asynchronous" processing using the "Prefer" HTTP Header as defined in Section 4.1
                            <xref target="RFC7240"/>. The client may do this for a number of reasons such as: avoiding
                            holding HTTP connections open during long requests, because the result of the request is not
                            needed, or for co-ordination reasons where the result is delivered to another entity for
                            further action.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            To initiate an async SCIM request, a normal SCIM protocol POST, PUT,
                            PATCH, or DELETE request is performed with the HTTP Header <tt>Prefer</tt> with a value of
                            <tt>respond-async</tt> as defined in <xref target="RFC9110"/>. The HTTP <tt>Accept</tt>
                            header SHALL be ignored.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            In response, and as indicated in the SCIM Service Provider Configuration (see
                            <xref target="serviceProviderConfig"/>, The SCIM Service Provider responds with either a
                            normal SCIM response, or respond asynchronously by returning HTTP Status 202 Accepted.
                            The asynchronous response SHOULD contain no response body. To enable correlation of the
                            future event, the HTTP response header "Set-txn" is returned.
                            The value SHALL correspond to a future Security Event Token to be received whose "txn" claim
                            SHALL match. The <tt>Location</tt> header returned SHALL be one of the following:
                        </t>
                        <ul>
                            <li>A location URI where the completion token MAY be retrieved using HTTP GET, or</li>
                            <li>The normal SCIM location header response specified by <xref target="RFC7644"/>.</li>
                        </ul>
                        <t keepWithNext="true">
                            In the following non-normative example, a "Prefer" header is set to "respond-async":
                        </t>
                        <figure anchor="asyncRequestFigure">
                            <name>Example Asynchronous SCIM Protocol Request</name>
                            <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width=""
                                     xml:space="preserve">
PUT /Users/2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646
Host: scim.example.com
Prefer: respond-async
Content-Type: application/scim+json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
{
  "schemas":["urn:ietf:params:scim:schemas:core:2.0:User"],
  "id":"2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646",
  "userName":"bjensen",
  "externalId":"bjensen",
  "name":{
    "formatted":"Ms. Barbara J Jensen III"
  },
  "roles":[],
  "emails":[
    {
        "value":"bjensen@example.com"
    }
  ]
}</artwork>

                        </figure>
                        <t keepWithNext="true">
                            The SCIM Service Provider responds with HTTP 202 Accepted and includes the Set-txn header:
                        </t>
                        <figure align="left" alt="" height="" suppress-title="false"
                                title="" width="">
                            <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width=""
                                     xml:space="preserve">HTTP/1.1 202 Accepted
Set-txn: 734f0614e3274f288f93ac74119dcf78
Location:
  "/Users/2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646"
           </artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                    <name>urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:misc:asyncResp</name>
                    <t>
                        The Async Response event signals the completion of a SCIM request. The event payload contains
                        the attributes defined in SCIM Bulk Section 3.7 <xref target="RFC7644"/> and is the same a
                        single SCIM Bulk Response Operation as per Section 3.7.3. In the event, the "txn" claim must be
                        set to the value originally returned to the requesting SCIM client (see <xref target="asyncRequest"/>).
                    </t>

                    <figure anchor="exampleAsyncEvent">
                        <name>Example SCIM Async Response Event</name>
                        <artwork type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[{
  "jti": "6164f3bbf6ff41a88dc94f18cb0620e8",
  "sub_id": {
    "format": "scim",
    "uri": "/Users/2819c223-7f76-453a-919d-413861904646"
  },
  "txn": "734f0614e3274f288f93ac74119dcf78",
  "events":{
    "urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:misc:asyncResp": {
        "method": "PUT",
        "version": "W\/\"huJj29dMNgu3WXPD\"",
        "status": "200"
    }
  },
  "iat": 1458505044,
  "iss":"https://scim.example.com",
  "aud":[
   "https://scim.example.com/Feeds/98d52461fa5bbc879593b7754"
  ]
}]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>

        </section>
        <section anchor="distribution" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Event Delivery Feeds</name>
            <t>
                In addition to retrieving a single security event as described in <xref target="asyncRequest"/>, Event
                Feeds (or Streams) provide the ability exchange a series of events between pre-arranged endpoints using
                the following Security Event Token exchange methods:
            </t>
            <dl newline="true">
                <dt><xref target="RFC8935"/></dt>
                <dd>
                    Push-Based Security Event Token (SET) Delivery delivers tokens to an Event Receiver with an accessible
                    HTTP Endpoint.
                </dd>
                <dt><xref target="RFC8936"/></dt>
                <dd>
                    Poll-Based Security Event Token (SET) Delivery enables an event receiver to initiate calls to SET Event
                    publisher endpoint to receive 1 or more events. This is particularly advantageous when an Event Receiver
                    is behind a firewall or other network restriction that would prevent Push Delivery. An Event Receiver
                    may also use HTTP "Long-polling" to achieve real time event delivery.
                </dd>
            </dl>
            <t>In the figure below, a possible distribution architecture is shown. This specification is only normatively
            concerned with the actual Security Event Transfer mechanism. SCIM Service providers MAY choose to implement
            SET transfer directly, or they may use a method of allowing a single Event Publisher to assemble streams of
            events for transfer to a receiver. Likewise, on the receiving side, the only normative requirement is to be
            able to receive events and implement storage of Events to local recovery needs.</t>
            <figure anchor="architecture">
                <artwork align="center" type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
┌───────────────┐  ┌───────────────┐    ┌───────────────┐
│               │  │               │    │               │
│ SCIM Server 1 │  │ SCIM Server 2 │ ...│ SCIM Server n │
│               │  │               │    │               │
└───────┬───────┘  └───────┬───────┘    └───────┬───────┘
        │                  │                    │
┌───────▼──────────────────▼────────────────────▼───────┐
│              Local Event Delivery System              │
└───────────────────────────┬───────────────────▲───────┘
                            │                   │
                   ┌────────▼────────┐   ┌──────┴───────┐
                   │                 │   │   Recovery   │
                   │ Event Publisher ◄───►    Buffer    │
                   │                 │   └──────────────┘
                   └────────┬────────┘
               ┌──          │
               │   ┌────────▼────────┐
               │   │ SET Trans Txmtr │
               │   │ (RFC 8935/8936) │
    Minimum    │   └────────┬────────┘
    Interop    │            │
    Requirement│            │
               │   ┌────────▼────────┐   ┌──────────────┐
               │   │  SET Trans Rcvr │   │     Event    │
               │   │ (RFC 8935/8936) ├───►    Storage   │
               │   └────────┬────────┘   └──────────────┘
               └──          │
                   ┌────────▼────────┐
                   │ Receiver Domain │
                   │ Event Processor │
                   └────────┬────────┘
                            │
                            ▼]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
                As Security Event Tokens are based on JWT tokens, it is possible to exchange events by a number of transfer
                mechanisms such as: XMPP <xref target="RFC6120"/>, HTTP <xref target="RFC9113"/>, and Message Buses (e.g.
                <xref target="RFC3259"/>, Apache Kafka <xref target="Kafka"/>). For example, on the publishing side, a
                cluster or network of SCIM servers may publish events to a common SET publisher service for distribution to 1 or more
                receivers. The Event Publisher MAY be incorporated directly into each SCIM Server, or a Local Event Delivery System
                might be used to collect events for an Event Publisher service for forwarding. How this is done is up
                to the implementer. This specification is only concerned with the interoperability of SET transfer between
                domains using <xref target="RFC8935"/> and <xref target="RFC8936"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
                The SET Transfer specifications provide a short-term method of recovery to ensure SET Events are successfully
                transferred. Once a receiving domain has successfully stored events to its own recovery needs, the receiving
                domain acknowledges the transfer of SET Events to the publisher using the method defined in <xref target="RFC8935"/> and <xref target="RFC8936"/>.
                SET does not specify local server event recovery mechanisms, this is up to the service implementation within
                each domain. This is done to enable cross-domain independence between domains. As an example, a hosted
                SCIM service provider with a series of SCIM servers replicates through a proprietary system. An enterprise
                customer who is the common client across both providers wants to establish a single administrative domain and
                wants to share SCIM change events between providers. Each domain has its own SCIM implementation and its own
                local replication strategy. The publishing domain issues events that the receiving domain picks up. Once the
                receiving domain has processed the event, the receiving domains own internal replication and recovery takes over.
                Because there is no need for the publishing domain to retain the event, it has the option to purge the event
                once the receiving domain has acknowledged it. This may be particularly critical if a publishing domain has dozens
                or even thousands of event receiving domains each with their own sub-set of data. Retaining all events for all
                receivers would become impractical.
            </t>
            <section anchor="jwtFormats">
                <name>Security Event Token Signing and Encryption</name>
                <t>
                    This specification uses Security Event Tokens as the message format for SCIM Events. As SETs are based
                    on JWT tokens <xref target="RFC7519"/>,
                    they can be transmitted insecurely, signed, or encrypted. For more information see the JWT Cookbook
                    specification <xref target="RFC7520"/> for examples. The decision on whether to use JWS and JWE depends
                    on operational considerations. For each SCIM Feed relationship, it is up to deployers to decide on
                    signing, encryption and algorithm requirements. Deployers SHOULD be aware that too much emphasis on
                    turning on every possible encryption feature may cause operational performance to suffer. Deployers
                    MUST weigh the security trade-offs of up-to-date SCIM services, vs. the potential information loss
                    of an event.
                </t>
                <dl newline="true">
                    <dt>Unsecured</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Per Section 6 <xref target="RFC7519"/>, tokens MAY be generated with <tt>{"alg":"none"}</tt>.
                        This mode speeds up processing and is best used in DBR scenarios. Unencrypted tokens MUST be
                        transferred over authenticated TLS layer encryption and SHOULD only be used in a restricted
                        network environment.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>Signed</dt>
                    <dd>
                        JWS (<xref target="RFC7515"/>) signed SETs are useful when it is important to be able to verify
                        the issuer of a SET as valid.
                        In addition, some systems MAY wish to validate the authenticity of the event in a review
                        process which may occur at a later date. While the content can be validated as originating from
                        the correct issuer and is unmodified, the message contents remain unsecure. Signed SETs MUST
                        be transferred over encrypted transport.
                    </dd>
                    <dt>Encrypted</dt>
                    <dd>
                        JWE (<xref target="RFC7516"/>) are encrypted SETs and are useful when the transport mechanism is
                        not fully secured (e.g. messages carried by a third party). The use of JWEs ensures only the
                        designated receiver can read the event and provides mutual authentication within the SET message
                        itself.
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>

            <section anchor="setDelivery" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Point-to-Point Delivery Over HTTP</name>
                <t>
                    Security Event Tokens MAY be delivered using push-based HTTP delivery <xref target="RFC8935"/>, or
                    pull-based HTTP Polling <xref target="RFC8936"/>. Both of these protocols define a method of
                    transfer and acknowledgement to prevent loss-of-information and to provide re-transmission and
                    recover. The method of transfer is best decided by considering the following advantages and disadvantages
                    in a production scenario:</t>
                <t>
                    Push-based delivery has the following advantages:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Message transfer is instant (when compared to using a common Event Publisher acting as a relay),
                        and in high event frequency scenarios, HTTP connections can be kept open.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Scales well when an SCIM Event Publisher has thousands of event receivers and TCP resources may
                        be limited.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Does not require events to be routed to a single publisher node. SCIM Events may be issued by
                        SCIM Service Provider nodes where the transaction occurred.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        SCIM Events only need to be retained until they have been delivered to designated receivers.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <t>
                    Push-delivery has the following disadvantages:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        A SCIM Event Publisher system needs authorization credentials enabling it to access the HTTP
                        SCIM Event delivery endpoint.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        When synchronizing business data that is behind protected firewalls, a virtual network or
                        other firewall policy may be required to allow external network based SCIM providers to
                        deliver SCIM Events to internally hosted systems.
                    </li>
                </ul>

                <t>
                    Delivery by HTTP Polling has the following advantages:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        It is possible for a SCIM Event Receiver to use the same SCIM credentials it uses when
                        access the normal SCIM Service Provider service defined by <xref target="RFC7644"/>.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Systems behind protected network boundaries can reach externally hosted systems without
                        requiring special firewall or network configuration.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Instantaneous transfer MAY be supported using HTTP Long-polling as described Section 2.1 of
                        <xref target="RFC8936"/>.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <t>
                    Polling-based delivery has the following disadvantages:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Long-polling requires the use of persistent connections for which TCP resources may be
                        limited. HTTP Long-polling is best used in scenarios when there are relatively few Event
                        Receivers.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The SCIM Event Publisher MUST retain events for the Event Receiver until delivered.
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="serviceProviderConfig" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Events Discovery Schema for Service Provider Configuration</name>
            <t>Section 5 of <xref target="RFC7643"/> defines SCIM Service Provider configuration schema. This section
            defines additional attributes that enable a SCIM client to discover the additional capabilities defined
            by this specification.</t>
            <dl newline="true">
                <dt>securityEvents</dt>
                <dd>
                    <t>
                        A SCIM Complex attribute that specifies the available capabilities
                        related to asynchronous Security Events based on <xref target="RFC8417"/>. This attribute is OPTIONAL and
                        when absent indicates the SCIM server does not support or is not currently configured for Security Events.
                        The following sub-attributes are defined: </t>
                    <dl newline="true">
                        <dt>asyncRequest</dt>
                        <dd>
                            <t>
                                A string value specifying one of the following:</t>
                                <ul>
                                    <li><tt>NONE</tt> indicates async SCIM requests defined in <xref target="asyncRequest"/> are not supported; </li>
                                    <li><tt>LONG</tt> indicates the SCIM Service Provider MAY complete asynchronously at its discretion (e.g.
                                    based on a max wait time);</li>
                                    <li><tt>REQUEST</tt> indicates the request SHALL complete asynchronously when requested by
                                        the SCIM Client.</li>
                                </ul>
                        </dd>
                        <dt>eventUris</dt>
                        <dd>
                            <t>
                                A multivalued string listing the SET Event URIs (defined in <xref target="RFC8417"/>)
                                the server is capable of generating and deliverable via a SET Stream (see <xref target="RFC8935"/> and <xref target="RFC8936"/>).
                                This information is informational only. Stream registration and configuration is out of scope of this specification.
                            </t>
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </dd>
            </dl>



        </section>
        <section anchor="Security" toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>Security Considerations</name>
            <t>
                This specification depends on the Security Considerations for <xref target="RFC8417"/>. </t>
            <t>
                The use of Json Web Encryption (JWE) <xref target="RFC7516"/> can impose performance limitations when
                used in high event frequency scenarios. JWE is primarily useful only when the transfer of SETs involves an
                unsecured transfer method (e.g. URL) that would not otherwise be protected by the transfer protocol (e.g.
                SET Transfer over TLS <xref target="RFC8446"/>).</t>
            <t>
                For SCIM Provisioning events, the long-term series of changes may be critical to both sides. As such
                Event Publishers SHOULD consider storing events for receivers for longer periods of time in the case of
                an extended SET Transfer service failure. Similarly, Event Receivers MUST ensure events are persisted
                directly or indirectly sufficient to meet local recovery needs before acknowledging received SET Events.
            </t>
            <t>
                When SET Events are stored for future delivery or retained local recovery MUST be limited only to the
                parties needed to support recovery or SET forwarding.
            </t>
            <t>
                JWS <xref target="RFC7515"/> signed SET Events SHOULD be used to verify authenticity of the origin of
                a SET Event. Validating event signatures is both useful on the initial transfer of SET Events, and
                may also be useful for auditing purposes.
            </t>
            <t>
                In operation, some SCIM resources such as SCIM Groups may have a high rate of change. Implementors and
                operators SHOULD consider use of throttling techniques to balance immediacy and frequency. For example, a
                large group whose members change dozens of times per second may not need discrete SET Patch Events per change.
                Instead, issuing a single consolidated change per second or even minute may be beneficial to keeping Event Receivers
                up-to-date. Likewise, a Co-ordinated Provisioning Event Receiver (Section 2.2), does not necessarily need to retrieve
                the full Group on every change request. It MAY choose to do lookups on a less frequent scale for reconciliation.
            </t>
            <t>
                When using Asynchronous SCIM Requests (see <xref target="asyncRequest"/>), and location returned in
                a SCIM Accepted response is a URI for retrieving the event result, the URI SHOULD be protected requiring
                an HTTP Authorization header. Or in the alternative, the SET's retrieved SHOULD be encrypted in order to
                authenticate the receiver. The retrieval endpoint SHOULD be protected
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Privacy" toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
            <t>This specification enables the sharing of information between domains. The specification assumes
            that implementers and deployers are operating under one of the following scenarios:
            </t>
            <ul>
                <li>A common administrative domain where there is one administrative owner of the data. In these cases
                the objective is to protect privacy and security of the owner and user data by keeping information
                systems co-ordinated and up-to-date. For example, the domains decide to use Domain Based Replication
                mode in order to keep employee information synchronized.</li>
                <li>In a co-operative or co-ordinated relationship, parties have decided to share a limited amount
                of data and or signals for the benefits of their users. Depending on end-user consent, information
                is shared on an as authorized and/or as needed basis. For example, the domains agree to use Co-ordinated
                Provision mode that exchanges things like account status, or specific minimal attribute information needed
                that must be fetched on request after receiving notice of a change. This enables authorization to
                be verified each time data is transferred.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>In general the sharing of SCIM Event information falls within a pre-existing SCIM Client and Service
            Provider relationship. In the case of SCIM Risk Signals Events, the existing relationship may need to be
            reviewed. By their nature, however, SCIM Signals carry no personal information and aid parties in ensuring
            the protection of privacy information and account security.</t>
            <t>Privacy considerations of <xref target="RFC8417"/> MUST also be observed.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>IANA Considerations</name>
            <section anchor="IANAheader" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>SCIM Async Txn Header Registration</name>
                <t>
                    This section registers the HTTP 'set-txn' header field in the "Permanent Message Header Field Names" registry
                    defined in <xref target="RFC3864"/>.
                </t>
                <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                    <dt>Header field name:</dt><dd>Set-txn</dd>
                    <dt>Applicable Protocol:</dt><dd>HTTP</dd>
                    <dt>Status:</dt><dd>Standard</dd>
                    <dt>Author:</dt><dd>IETF</dd>
                    <dt>Specification Document:</dt><dd>this specification, <xref target="attributes"/> and <xref target="asyncRequest"/>. </dd>
                    <dt>Related information:</dt><dd>See also: Section 2.2 <xref target="RFC8417"/>.</dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="IANAevents" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>SCIM Events Registry</name>
            <t>This section registers a new type called "event" in the SCIM Namespace registry found in
                <xref target="scimEvents" format="default"/>
                in the SCIM registry as per
                <xref target="RFC7643" format="default">Section 10.2.1</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>This new event namespace shall take the structure: <tt>urn:ietf:params:scim:event:{class}:{name}:{other}</tt></t>

            <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
                <dt>Schema URI:</dt>
                <dd>See<xref target="scimEvents" format="default"/>.
                </dd>
                <dt>Schema Name:</dt>
                <dd>See corresponding names under<xref target="scimEvents" format="default"/>.
                </dd>
                <dt>Intended ResourceType:</dt>
                <dd>N/A. Events are not intended to be persisted in SCIM and will be used with Security Event Tokens
                    <xref target="RFC8417"/>.</dd>
                <dt>Purpose:</dt>
                <dd>See each description in<xref target="scimEvents" format="default"/>.
                </dd>
                <dt>Single-valued Attributes:</dt>
                <dd>None.</dd>
                <dt>Multi-valued Attributes:</dt>
                <dd>All schemas in this specification share the same attributes. See<xref target="attributes"
                                                                                          format="default"/>.
                </dd>
            </dl>
            <t keepWithNext="true">Summary of schema URI registrations:</t>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th align="left">Schema URI</th>
                        <th align="left">Name</th>
                        <th align="left">Ref.</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:add</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource added to Feed Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="feedAdd" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:feed:remove</td>
                        <td align="left">Remove resouce From Feed Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="feedRemove" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:create:
                            notice</td>
                        <td align="left">New Resource Event (notice only)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provCreate" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:create:
                            full</td>
                        <td align="left">New Resource Event (full data)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provCreate" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:patch:
                            notice</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Patch Event (notice only)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provPatch" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:patch:
                            full</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Patch Event (full data)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provPatch" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:put:
                            notice</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Put Event (notice only)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provPut" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:put:full</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Put Event (full data)</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provPut" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:delete</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Deleted Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provDelete" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:activate</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Activated Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provActivate" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:prov:deactivate</td>
                        <td align="left">Resource Deactivated Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="provDeactivate" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:authMethod</td>
                        <td align="left">New authentication method added</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="authMethod" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="left">urn:ietf:params:SCIM:event:sig:pwdReset</td>
                        <td align="left">Password Reset Event</td>
                        <td align="left">
                            <xref target="sigPassReset" format="default"/>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
            </section>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references>
            <name>References</name>
            <references>
                <name>Normative References</name>

                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7240.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7516.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7643.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7644.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8417.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/>
                <reference anchor="SUBID">
                    <front>
                        <title>Subject Identifiers for Security Event Tokens (Draft 18)</title>
                        <author fullname="A. Backman, Ed">
                            <organization>Amazon</organization></author>
                        <author fullname="M. Scurtescu">
                            <organization>Coinbase</organization>
                        </author>
                        <author fullname="P. Jain"><organization>Fastly</organization></author>
                        <date year="2023" day="24" month="June"/>
                    </front>
                    <format target="https://www.ietf.org/archive/id/draft-ietf-secevent-subject-identifiers-18.txt"
                            type="HTML"/>
                </reference>

            </references>

            <references>
                <name>Informative References</name>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3259.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3864.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6120.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7520.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9113.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8935.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8936.xml"/>
                <reference anchor="Kafka">
                    <front>

                        <title>Apache Kafka </title>
                        <author><organization>Apache Software Foundation</organization></author>
                        <date year="2017"/>
                    </front>
                    <format target="https://kafka.apache.org"
                            type="HTML"/>
                </reference>
                <referencegroup anchor="SSWG">
                    <reference anchor="SSEF">
                        <front>
                            <title>OpenID Shared Signals and Events Framework Specification 1.0 - draft 01</title>
                            <author fullname="A. Tulshibagwale">
                                <organization>Google</organization>
                            </author>
                            <author fullname="T. Cappalli">
                                <organization>Microsoft</organization>
                            </author>
                            <author fullname="M. Scurtescu">
                                <organization>Coinbase</organization>
                            </author>
                            <author fullname="A. Backman">
                                <organization>Amazon</organization>
                            </author>
                            <author fullname="J. Bradley">
                                <organization>Yubico</organization>
                            </author>
                            <date year="2021" month="June" day="8"/>
                            <abstract>
                                <t>
                                    This Shared Signals and Events (SSE) Framework enables sharing of signals and events between cooperating peers. It enables multiple applications such as Risk Incident Sharing and Coordination (RISC) and the Continuous Access Evaluation Profile,
                                </t>
                            </abstract>

                        </front>
                        <format target="https://openid.net/specs/openid-sse-framework-1_0-ID1.html"
                                type="HTML"/>
                    </reference>
                    <reference anchor="CAEP">
                        <front>

                            <title>OpenID Continuous Access Evaluation Profile 1.0 - draft 02</title>
                            <author fullname="T. Cappalli">
                                <organization>Microsoft</organization>
                            </author>
                            <author fullname="AA. Tulshibagwale">
                                <organization>Google</organization>
                            </author>
                            <date year="2021" month="June" day="8"/>
                            <abstract>
                                <t>
                                    This document defines the Continuous Access Evaluation Profile (CAEP) of the Shared Signals and Events Framework. It specifies a set of event types conforming to the SSE Framework. These event types are intended to be used between cooperating Transmitters and Receivers such that Transmitters may send continuous updates using which Receivers can attenuate access to shared human or robotic users, devices, sessions and applications.
                                </t>
                            </abstract>

                        </front>
                        <format target="https://openid.net/specs/openid-caep-specification-1_0-ID1.html"
                                type="HTML"/>
                    </reference>

                </referencegroup>

            </references>
        </references>
        <section anchor="modes" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Use Cases</name>
            <t>
                SCIM Events may be used in a number of ways. The following non-normative sections describe some of
                the expected uses.
            </t>

            <section anchor="replication" toc="default" numbered="true">
                <name>Domain Based Replication</name>
                <t>
                    The objective of "Domain Based Replication" events (DBR) is to synchronize resource changes between
                    SCIM service providers in a common administrative domain. In this mode, complete information about
                    changes for resources are shared between replicas for immediate processing.
                </t>
                <figure align="left" anchor="dbrSequence">
                    <name>Domain Based Replication Sequence</name>
                    <artset>
                        <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
                    ┌────────────────┐
┌────────┐          │SCIM            │   ┌────────────────────────┐
│Client A│          │Service Provider│   │Service Provider Replica│
└───┬────┘          └───────┬────────┘   └───────────┬────────────┘
    │   "SCIM Operation"   ┌┴┐                       │
    │ ────────────────────>│ │                       │
    │                      │ │                       │
    │   "SCIM Response"    │ │                      ┌┴┐
    │ <────────────────────│ │                      │ │
    │                      └┬┘                      │ │
    │                       │  "Event SCIM:prov:<op>│ │
    │                       │  id:xyz"              │ │
    │                       │ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─>│ │
    │                       │                       │ │
    │                       │                       │ │
    │                       │                       │ │────┐
                                 "Update local node"│ │    │
                                                    │ │<───┘
                                                    └┬┘]]></artwork>
                        <artwork align="center" type="svg">
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="1.1" viewBox="0 0 697.0 550.0">

                                <!-- Generator: Sequence Diagram - v1.8.11-(198) - http://www.macsequencediagram.com -->

                                <rect x="0.0" y="0.0" width="697.0" height="594.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0"/>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="60.0" y="60.0" width="129.0" height="61.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="124.5" y="90.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Client A</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="209.0" y="50.0" width="180.0" height="82.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="299.0" y="82.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">SCIM</text>
                                    <text x="299.0" y="99.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Service Provider</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="409.0" y="60.0" width="228.0" height="61.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="523.0" y="90.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Service Provider Replica</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="124.0" y1="121.0" x2="126.0" y2="472.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="298.0" y1="132.0" x2="300.0" y2="462.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="522.0" y1="121.0" x2="524.0" y2="472.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineActivationBoxView">
                                    <rect x="291.0" y="193.0" width="16.0" height="115.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineActivationBoxView">
                                    <rect x="515.0" y="300.0" width="16.0" height="56.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="208.0" y="180.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[1] SCIM Operation</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="208.0" y="225.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[2] SCIM Response</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="415.0" y="271.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[3] Event SCIM:prov:&lt;op&gt;</text>
                                    <text x="415.0" y="287.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">id:xyz</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="511.0" y="332.5" text-anchor="end" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[4] Update local node</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 281.0,192.0 L 291.0,197.5 L 281.0,202.0 L 281.0, 192.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="125.0" y1="197.5" x2="281.0" y2="197.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 135.0,237.0 L 125.0,242.5 L 135.0,247.0 L 135.0, 237.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="135.0" y1="242.5" x2="291.0" y2="242.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 505.0,299.0 L 515.0,304.5 L 505.0,309.0 L 505.0, 299.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="307.0" y1="304.5" x2="505.0" y2="304.5" stroke-dasharray="5.0, 3.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 541.0,342.0 L 530.5,346.5 L 541.0,352.0 L 541.0,342.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>
                                    <line x1="531.5" y1="324.5" x2="570.5" y2="324.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <line x1="570.5" y1="346.5" x2="541.0" y2="346.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <path d="M 570.5,324.5 Q 580.5,324.5 580.5, 334.5 L 580.5 336.5 Q 580.5,346.5 570.5,346.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>

                                <!-- Generator: Sequence Diagram - v1.8.11-(198) - http://www.macsequencediagram.com -->

                            </svg>

                        </artwork>
                    </artset>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    From a security perspective, it is assumed that servers sharing DBR events are secured by a common
                    access policy and all servers are required to be up-to-date.
                    From a Privacy Perspective, because all servers are in the same administrative domain, the primary objective
                    is to keep individual service provider nodes or cluster synchronized.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="coordination" toc="default" numbered="true">
                <name>Co-ordinated Provisioning</name>
                <t>
                    In "Co-ordinated Provisioning" (CP), SCIM resource change events perform the function of change
                    notification without the need to provide raw data. In any Event Publisher and Receiver
                    relationship, the set of SCIM resources (e.g. Users) that are linked or co-ordinated is managed
                    within the context of an event feed and which MAY be a subset of the total set of resources on
                    either side. For example, an event feed could be limited to users who have consented to the sharing
                    of information between domains. To support capability, "feed" specific events are defined to indicate
                    the addition and removal of SCIM resources from a feed. For example, when a user consents to
                    the sharing of information between domains, events about the User MAY be added to the feed
                    between the Event Publisher and Receiver.
                </t>
                <figure align="left">
                    <name>Co-Ordinated Provisioning Sequence</name>
                    <artset>
                        <artwork type="ascii-art" align="center"><![CDATA[
               ┌────────────────┐  ┌──────────────┐  ┌─────────────┐
┌───────────┐  │SCIM            │  │Client A      │  │Co-op Action │
│SCIM Client│  │Service Provider│  │Co-op Receiver│  │Endpoint     │
└─────┬─────┘  └───────┬────────┘  └──────┬───────┘  └───────┬─────┘
      │ "SCIM Ope"    ┌┴┐                 │                  │
      │──────────────>│ │                 │                  │
      │               │ │                 │                  │
      │ "SCIM Resp"   │ │                ┌┴┐                 │
      │<──────────────│ │                │ │                 │
      │               │ │                │ │                 │
      │               │ │                │ │                 │
      │      ╔═══════╤╪═╪════════════════╪═╪═════════════════╪════╗
      │      ║ LOOP  ││ │                │ │                 │    ║
      │      ╟───────┘└┬┘ Event:         │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │   SCIM:prov:<op>│ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │  id:xyz         │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │  ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ ─ >│ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │                 │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │    ╔════════════╧═╧══════════════╗  │    ║
      │      ║         │    ║Receiver may accumulate      ║  │    ║
      │      ║         │    ║events for periodic action.  ║  │    ║
      │      ║         │    ╚════════════╤═╤══════════════╝  │    ║
      │      ║         │ SCIM GET <id>   │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │ <───────────────│ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │                 │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │ Filtered        │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │ Resource Resp   │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │ ───────────────>│ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │                 │ │                 │    ║
      │      ║         │                 │ │ "Co-ord Action" │    ║
      │      ║         │                 │ │ ───────────────>│    ║
      │      ╚═════════╪═════════════════╪═╪═════════════════╪════╝]]></artwork>
                        <artwork type="svg" align="center">
                            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="1.1" viewBox="0 0 912.0 857.0">

                                <!-- Generator: Sequence Diagram - v1.8.11-(198) - http://www.macsequencediagram.com -->

                                <rect x="0.0" y="0.0" width="912.0" height="857.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0"/>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="60.0" y="70.0" width="154.0" height="61.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="137.0" y="100.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">SCIM Client</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="234.0" y="60.0" width="180.0" height="82.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="324.0" y="92.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">SCIM</text>
                                    <text x="324.0" y="109.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Service Provider</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="434.0" y="60.0" width="177.0" height="82.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="522.5" y="92.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Client A</text>
                                    <text x="522.5" y="109.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Co-op Receiver</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="ParticipantView">
                                    <rect x="631.0" y="70.0" width="221.0" height="61.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" stroke="#000000" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="741.5" y="100.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Co-op Action Endpoint</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="136.0" y1="131.0" x2="138.0" y2="735.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="323.0" y1="142.0" x2="325.0" y2="725.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="522.0" y1="142.0" x2="524.0" y2="725.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineView">
                                    <line x1="741.0" y1="131.0" x2="743.0" y2="735.0" stroke-dasharray="20.0, 10.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineActivationBoxView">
                                    <rect x="316.0" y="213.0" width="16.0" height="160.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="LifelineActivationBoxView">
                                    <rect x="515.0" y="365.0" width="16.0" height="234.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="InteractionFrameView">
                                    <rect x="269.0" y="287.0" width="528.0" height="328.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="0.0"/>
                                    <path d="M 269.0,287.0 L 324.0,287.0 L 324.0,295.0 L 318.0,303.0 L 269.0,303.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <rect x="269.0" y="287.0" width="528.0" height="328.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="296.5" y="295.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="12.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">    loop    </text>
                                    <text x="344.0" y="295.0" text-anchor="start" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="12.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="226.5" y="200.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[1] SCIM Operation</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="226.5" y="245.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[2] SCIM Response</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="427.5" y="336.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[3] Event SCIM:prov:&lt;op&gt;</text>
                                    <text x="427.5" y="352.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">id:xyz</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="419.5" y="471.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[4] SCIM GET &lt;id&gt;</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="419.5" y="517.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[5] Filtered</text>
                                    <text x="419.5" y="533.0" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Resource Response</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalMessageView">
                                    <text x="636.5" y="578.5" text-anchor="middle" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="13.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">[6] Co-ordinated Action</text>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 306.0,212.0 L 316.0,217.5 L 306.0,222.0 L 306.0, 212.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="137.0" y1="217.5" x2="306.0" y2="217.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 147.0,257.0 L 137.0,262.5 L 147.0,267.0 L 147.0, 257.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="147.0" y1="262.5" x2="316.0" y2="262.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 505.0,364.0 L 515.0,369.5 L 505.0,374.0 L 505.0, 364.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="332.0" y1="369.5" x2="505.0" y2="369.5" stroke-dasharray="5.0, 3.0" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 334.0,483.0 L 324.0,488.5 L 334.0,493.0 L 334.0, 483.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="334.0" y1="488.5" x2="515.0" y2="488.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 505.0,545.0 L 515.0,550.5 L 505.0,555.0 L 505.0, 545.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="324.0" y1="550.5" x2="505.0" y2="550.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="SignalLineView">
                                    <path d="M 732.0,590.0 L 742.0,595.5 L 732.0,600.0 L 732.0, 590.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0"/>

                                    <line x1="531.0" y1="595.5" x2="732.0" y2="595.5" fill="none" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                </g>
                                <g class="NoteView">
                                    <rect x="429.0" y="379.0" width="188.0" height="54.0" rx="5.0" ry="5.0" fill="#FFFFFF" fill-opacity="1.0" stroke="#000000" stroke-opacity="1.0" stroke-width="1.0"/>
                                    <text x="443.0" y="397.5" text-anchor="start" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">Receiver may accumulate</text>
                                    <text x="443.0" y="414.5" text-anchor="start" font-family="sans-serif" font-size="14.0" fill="#000000" fill-opacity="1.0">events for periodic action.</text>
                                </g>

                                <!-- Generator: Sequence Diagram - v1.8.11-(198) - http://www.macsequencediagram.com -->

                            </svg>

                        </artwork>
                    </artset>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    In CP mode, the receiver of an event must call back to the originating SCIM Service Provider
                    (e.g. using a SCIM GET request) to reconcile the newly changed resource in
                    order to obtain the changes.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Co-ordinated provisioning has the following benefits:
                </t>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Differences in schema (e.g. attributes) between domains. For example, a receiving domain may
                        only be interested or only be allowed access to a few attributes (e.g. role based access data) to enable access to an
                        application.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Different Event Receivers MAY have differing needs access to information and thus be assigned
                        varying access rights. Minimal information events combined with call-backs for data allows
                        data filtering to be applied.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Receivers can take independent action. For example deciding which attributes or resource lifecycle
                        changes to accept. For example, in the case of a conflict, a receiver can prioritize one domain
                        source over another.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        A receiver MAY throttle or buffer changes rather than act immediately on a notification. For
                        example, for a frequently changing resource, the
                        receiver MAY choose to make scheduled SCIM GET for resources that have been marked "dirty" by
                        events received in the last scheduled cycle.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <t>
                    A disadvantage of the CP approach is that it may be considered costly in the sense that each event
                    received might trigger a call back to the event issuer. This cost should be weighed against the cost
                    producing filtered information in each event for each receiver. Further a receiver is not required
                    to make a call-back on every provisioning event.
                </t>

                <t>
                    It is assumed that an underlying relationship between domains exists that permits the exchange of
                    personal information and credentials. For example the decision to perform SCIM provisioning operations
                    at the SCIM Service Provider issuing change events, was previously authorized
                    and appropriate confidentiality and privacy agreements have been met in cross-domain scenarios. Examples
                    of this might be services for hire by an employer or a specific consent from an end-user as part
                    of a online authorization where individual consent was obtained.
                </t>
                <t>
                    When sharing information between parties, CP Events minimize the information shared in each message
                    requiring the Security Event Receiver to call back to the event publisher to retrieve more information
                    if required. In this way, the Event Publisher is able to regular access to information through normal
                    SCIM protocol access restrictions.
                </t>

            </section>
            <section anchor="s_risk" toc="default" numbered="true">
                <name>Risk Signals</name>
                <t>
                    The sharing of risk signals (RS) is used for the purpose of co-ordinating account change events between
                    a SCIM Service Provider and another related security service. For example, when a password or other
                    authentication factor has changed, a receiving security system can choose to terminate current User
                    sessions to force a re-authentication against the modified User resource.
                </t>
                <t>
                    These signals MAY also include those described in the
                    <xref target="SSWG">OpenID Shared Signals Working Group Specifications</xref>.
                </t>
                <t>
                    These events are intended for receivers where there is a prior relationship on behalf of the users
                    described in the SCIM Service Provider. The intent of sharing information about security events is
                    for the purpose of securing a user account and ensuring privacy.
                </t>

            </section>

        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Acknowledgments</name>
            <t>
                Thanks to Morteza Ansari who contributed significantly to draft-hunt-idevent-scim-00, upon which this
                draft is based.</t>
            <t>
                The editor would like to thank the participants in the SCIM
                working group and the id-event list for their support of this specification.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Change Log</name>
            <t>Draft 00 - PH - First WG Draft</t>
            <t>Draft 01 - PH - Moved non-normative sections to Appendix, Security and Privacy Considerations</t>
            <t>Draft 02 - PH - Clarifications on Async Events, IANA Considerations</t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
